I'm not sure how we're going to roll through this, and apologies for the timban
along the chair. So,
we've had the report. I have actually gone through it, and I flicked through it
again last night.
Is this what we're focusing on?
It is. That's right.
Right. Would you like to take us through it?
Yes. So what I'll do is, Matt and I will just introduce ourselves and then
do some brief introductory comments, and then we'll open up questions pretty much.
Okay.
So, good morning, everybody. I'm Sarah Munson.
I'm the Deputy Secretary, Capability Delivery for the Ministry of
Defence, which basically means I'm the head of acquisition for what the ministry
buys. With me is Brigadier Matt Weston, who is also
involved in capability acquisition.
This is the 16th report that the ministry has provided to this
committee. We first published it in 2010, and the purpose
is to give greater visibility and scrutiny of the major
projects that the ministry runs, with support from
NZDF.
There's information in the report relating to seven projects and two programs.
And I just wanted to note that over the last 12 months, while focusing on the
delivery of these projects, we've also been doing a
significant amount of work with New Zealand industry.
And much of my time and Matt's time is involved in working with New Zealand
industry and
looking for opportunities as much as possible to make sure that the significant
investment government's making into defense is distributed into the New Zealand
economy.
Thanks, Sarah. Kia ora.
Just a couple of quick comments from me.
I think it's important to note that, whilst we're talking about the major
projects report today, NZDF is managing over 300
other capability-related projects, typically of lower scale and
risk than what you see in your report today.
One of those projects is the technology accelerator, which is going to be a
really important part of how we move forward in terms of innovation and
engagement with the New Zealand industry, and we're very excited about that
opportunity. We look forward to your questions.
Tech accelerator, that doesn't sound very good to me. That could apply to anything.
But anyway, I won't start there. There are people who know better.
Can I just really bluntly, opportunities for New Zealand industry, so
what kind of premium are we prepared to pay to give New
Zealanders an opportunity?
Well, I guess that is a question for government when they make the
case-by-case decisions. Our role is to present
opportunities to government as much as is possible, and we're
working with New Zealand industry, which there are some fantastic companies in New
Zealand that support defense. Some of them are considered dual use,
so they don't even consider themselves defense yet.
And the example I'd give would be precision engineering companies, where they can
make component parts
for our capabilities at a much cheaper and much faster rate than overseas.
So we're really trying to bring those companies through.
So it might not be that they build us a ship or an airplane, but they can build
the component parts that make a big difference, particularly in terms of resilience
in this part of the world.
So you're saying that
have a line up of companies and some are 20, 30% more
expensive. Do you eliminate them? How do you present those to government?
Well, through our procurement process, we do a cost-benefit
analysis for each of the companies that
we assess. So we do a tender, we'd evaluate them, we'd have criteria.
One of the criteria now in the new government procurement rules is value to the New
Zealand economy. So companies have to prove to us the contribution
they're making to the New Zealand economy.
Every tender has to do that,
and that's one of a number of evaluation criteria.
But we pretty much go for best value for money.
But if we think that there is opportunity for New Zealand industry that might
cost a little bit more than
maybe an international company, we would present that to government and we could
make a choice. It will be case by case as to whether or not we want to pay
more for a New Zealand company.
Yeah. Well, those are the easy questions. Right, Caroline?
Can I
ask about Aurek's 2 [C] , which is PBN introduction into
NH90, which says it's on a
2030 timeframe.
Correct.
What life of type are you planning for
NH90?
We're working essentially to the mid-2030s.
I guess the question is, is it really worth it, and are you
actually going to be able to deliver it?
Because has anyone else delivered PBN in NH90?
I think that as the NH90 club has reduced,
it is becoming more of a challenge. Yeah.
We've done a lot of work to
consider that very question. Do we want to upgrade at
a time
when we're starting to think about a future capability?
We did test that and it was decided that we did wish to keep a
military grade suite of capabilities on NH90 through
to its life type.
The NATO countries that have that helicopter are upgrading with
secure comms and PBN.
Yeah. So I take the secure comms point because I think that's in at the end of this
year.
You've already done the ADS-B outs for that.
NH90 has its own inbuilt
sort of precision guidance.
If it's just about a risk-based approach, can't you
lean on that
and take the military risk rather than
the... I'm just thinking of the amount of time and effort that's going to be put in
at step branch on the base to deliver something that you
may or may not ever use. Yeah. Look, what I would say
is, we're very concerned about how
your navigation timing can be disrupted with modern
adversary methods. So we've decided to keep to a military grade
Precision and timing are capability.
And
I understand that that's the decision you've taken.
You're going to get, what, at best, five years of
use out of that?
Yeah, essentially. Yes.
And it's going to take five years to deliver.
Yeah, I think we're--
we're still working with the
OEM to confirm the timelines, and it is part of that
NH90 club, so there is some negotiation required.
And just the final bit then, you said other European operators are looking
at this. This is other ones of the
TTH, the troop carrying variant, not the naval variant, I'm assuming.
But is that just something that they can roll out, or are we having to do
any bespoke design work for this?
We're not doing bespoke design work, but the work, the design work is being done by
NATO Helicopter Industries, the comp-- the OEM, the company that does it,
for the club, if you like. So, for the NATO countries,
including for New Zealand.
And we'll just get the same product that they developed that the Europeans get.
Yes.
We're not getting anything customized for...
And we're on the same software release as the European variants are.
Yeah. That's correct.
Thank you.
Chris.
Thank you, Mr. Chair. A couple of points if I may.
The first one is a little bit self-indulgent, but can I just take a moment to thank
both of you and the teams you work with?
I've been really grateful for our interaction.
I know that you're doing a really good job and working really hard,
for
defense, but also more broadly-
Might be a bit premature given that we haven't done a flippin' thing.
I'm, I'm-
It's an, it's an... I suppose it's insider trading on my part, really isn't it?
It's nice to see you.
Good to see you.
The work that you're doing. Thank you.
And I think, if I may say, you're right to emphasize the work that you've been
doing very closely with industry.
We've just met as a committee with a delegation from Japan and, of course,
naturally they've raised the possibility that we might purchase one of their Mikami
frigates. So you won't be surprised to hear that they raised that with us.
I know that there's a real emphasis in MOD and, dare I say, across
government generally, to make sure that
where there are platforms that we purchase,
inevitably from overseas because we're not building frigates in this country
anytime soon,
that we want
those who would sell kit to us to work with local
industry. And so do you mind just talking a bit about how we ensure that they are
aware of the opportunities in New Zealand to work alongside our defense, or,
to your point, Sarah, including with New Zealand entities that
don't even necessarily consider themselves to be defense suppliers at this time?
Good start. So, one of the ways that our big
prime companies get to know about the New Zealand companies is through the
Defense Industry Association, which do a really great job.
So that's one way that primes can.
We
do a lot of discussions with our international primes, talking to them about New
Zealand companies and introducing them.
And in fact, next week, Minister Goldsmith is
involved in a big event in Auckland run by Defense Industry Association where
he's speaking and will be the guest, I guess,
for international primes and New Zealand companies
to meet so that we are basically showcasing what New Zealand can
do. And we've done case by case,
we've had a lot of discussions where primes have come to us and said,
"We're interested in supply chain resilience in this part of the
world. Please introduce us to companies that can support us with that." And we
have been doing that.
Good one. Thank you.
Yes.
Shane.
Thank you. The cover page has a Te Mana in a dry dock, and I would
guess it was there probably for a year.
My question is, how useful would it be for the frigate sustainment program,
particularly envisaging that Canterbury may not even fit into Devonport Dry Dock to
have a further dry dock, is my question.
My initial answer is there is a lack of dry
dock capacity in this part of the world writ large.
Both us and other nations are using dry docks in places like
Singapore because there's just not enough capacity.
I must say, there's a level of interest from other militaries on
dry dock capacity in New Zealand.
I think,
yeah, I wouldn't wish to speak out further, but
certainly from a military perspective, dry dock capacity is an issue.
Thank you.
Can I come back to one of the projects you had, Bushmaster Communications?
And I guess it goes to the issue of communications in general and
kind of what platforms we are connected to and, I guess
the risk associated with that.
The traditional allies with the US and I guess the
US systems, they are being challenged, that assumption that they are our
best friend.
Can you explain firstly why there's a bit of a delay there?
Then what are the systems that we're putting in place and
kind of what's the oversight? Whose satellite system are we using, and what do we
know?
Okay.
If I talk to the Bushmaster first,
specifically.
When we started both the Bushmaster project or the vehicle
project and the Network Enabled Army project,
it was at a time when we'd been involved in the long counterinsurgencies
in Iraq and Afghanistan, and most of the focus on command and control was
from static forward operating bases.
Lessons from more recent conflicts like the Ukraine indicate that
if you
retain your command and control
headquarters in the land environment in a static location, it
gets killed really quickly, and that was a big feature of early on in the Ukraine
war.
Mm.
So with that, we realized that with the Bushmaster purchase,
we needed to integrate an ability to
communicate on the move into that vehicle.
But that has brought complications because it is an armored vehicle,
and essentially acts as what's known as a Faraday cage, so blocks
emissions in and out of it. So then to put your communications
into it is quite an almost retrofitting, is a quite
a big design and engineering fit. We've put an interim
system in, which gives us
two radios so we can communicate on two different radio nets.
But we're designing and building
a system which will allow us to access satellite communications on the move
and a range of radio types,
high frequency, very high frequency, which is our typical
tactical operating method, and move digital and
voice transmissions. So,
that is quite a complicated piece of engineering and design work.
And it's just going to take a while, unfortunately.
So, that's the Bushmaster piece.
Yes, you're right. We
operate
tactically at secret classification, so our
radios are all classified to provide
secret encryption,
which is quite a sophisticated
piece of engineering, I guess.
That is regularly updated based on assessments of what the
threat is and how potential adversaries could
look to
attack our encryption systems. So we're part of
a club where our encryption systems and our encryption gets
updated.
In terms of
satellite communication, any satellite we
communicate through has to meet certain requirements, and our
data as it moves from a ground station through the satellite is
encrypted as well to the appropriate level.
Does that answer the-
Hold on. I've got a question.
I'm just conscious of time and the committee, we have to finish
at 9:00 on the dot.
Yeah.
And I guess that there are many questions I'm sure
these technical guys could probably follow on.
Any questions now?
Okay.
Just mindful of the time.
Yeah, mindful of the time. I'll keep this pretty quick.
Do you think the settings are right between government and defense to
deliver procurement of all the new technologies fast enough?
And where do you think we could improve that process?
Because we're talking about quite a lot of layers
that have been in place in peacetime
operation.
We're now into a different,
what would you call it, phase?
Paradigm. Yeah.
Whatever. Paradigm.
Yeah.
I'm really conscious of the fact that the technologies are moving super quickly,
and
do you think you have the ability to procure and
deliver quick enough, and what could government do in order to make
that a lot easier?
I might leave the procurement piece to Sarah, if that's all right.
Sure. Do you want me to start with procurement?
Yeah. No, I could talk more generally-
Okay
... if that helps.
So, much of what
the ministry is involved in is big airplanes, big aeroplanes-
Mm-hmm
... big ships. They just take a certain amount of time.
Mm-hmm.
So it takes two or three years to build something.
So, that is problematic for us. There's also supply
chain
challenges for us in the world. Some of the smaller pieces of equipment,
particularly communications equipment, there may be a two-year lead time.
Mm-hmm.
So there are some things that we just can't do anything about other than we can
build good relationships internationally, which we do.
We can try and get as far up that order list as possible.
There are a lot of different contracting methods we can use to speed things up.
The government's recent changes to the procurement rules-
Mm-hmm
... have certainly assisted in us being able to do things
faster. We're always looking for ways to do things faster.
The other challenge for defense is making sure that the people are there and
suitably qualified when the equipment turns up.
And so that is also a over time process.
Mm-hmm.
There's no simple answer to this, but we're very aware that we need to do things
faster.
Australia is also trying to do things faster-
Mm-hmm
... as is the UK, and we're constantly with them, talking to them about how we
can-
Yeah
... learn their lessons.
Is there-- What work is being done with Australia to essentially
procure together? I know that there's been a lot of talk about this, but there is-
Yeah
... like they-- We've got Plan ANZAC.
They are-
Mm-hmm
... where essentially if we were in any form of conflict,
would we be adjoined or attached or working extremely closely
together?
Yes.
So is there argument for, yes, we've got New Zealand
Defense Industry, and I think that's great and we should be working in on that.
But at the same time-
Yeah
... what Australia's doing and where they're going with their procurement piece.
Yeah. Absolutely. Our interoperability with Australia is really important.
I would say their context is a little bit different than ours in terms
of
capacity, budget-
Mm-hmm
... even like geopolitical sort of settings are a little bit different.
But interoperability is an absolute must.
There are some areas where we can do that really well, and
you've just had the Japanese delegation here.
If we were to
choose to head towards the Mogami frigate, the key part of that decision would
actually be about what value would the relation having the same frigate as
Australia deliver-
Mm
... versus a different option. So, that would be central to that decision.
We've recently just finished,
in the counter UAS space, we're leveraging off what the Australian counter UAS
project is, and doing that so that we have the same systems and
also can utilize their capacity to
develop and design new tactics, techniques, and procedures.
Okay.
Yeah.
We've got three minutes, and I want one minute at the end to decide what we'll do.
You got it, sir?
Yeah. I guess the point that Laura makes
is, would we be more efficient if we just said-
Whatever force is getting, add to that.
It won't be 100% solution for us, but the amount of time over the years that we
have spent into these projects, and previously, and I think we're
getting away from that, but we tried to customize this and ended up with a whole
bunch of orphans in New Zealand.
Good.
If we just said, "Add 10% to what Australia are getting," and send them our way,
and saved all the manpower and all the effort, would we be in a pretty good place?
Look, I think we've adopted a new
methodology, which we're calling minimum
viable product.
That's not about the minimum cost, it's actually about reducing the schedule risk.
So what can we bring into service quickest
that will do the job well enough? And under that sort of
mindset, leveraging the Australian capacity,
and particularly if they're ahead of us on something, has obvious benefits,
yes. And as I say, Counter-UAS is a very recent example where we did
that very thing.
And also the Bluebottle UAV, is we just bought what Australia's got.
Yeah.
One minute.
Thank you very much. We'll just take a minute to work out whether...
It's quite a substantive, and I think obviously very interesting part of
oversight, of defense, so over the committee oversight.
But thank you very much, and we might call you back in again, possibly.
Okay.
That's all right.
Take a seat.
There's no election and we've got one and a half weeks left, so come on in.
You can probably relax for now. But the new committee might be really interested
in-
Well, sorry. We can-
I could move to extend by 10 minutes the time for the
select committee. Just we think that covers it.
I'm free. Are you free?
Yep.
We can do 10 minutes.
That's fine.
Right. We'll extend by 10 minutes.
Okay.
Okay. So sorry.
Sorry.
That's fine.
Take a seat.
Carry on.
I'll put my glasses back on.
So we're all on questions?
Yeah. So, I
think there's a real conceptual question there about how we do this,
and I take that, the minimum viable approach.
But I also just think it's about cutting out the tune and the agility to move
really quickly by
blatantly letting Australia do all the hard work for us and then go, "Well, we
operate in a different environment here."
Mm-hmm.
I accept that, but in theater, we work in the exact same environment.
Totally.
So if it's going to work for them, it should work for us.
Can I just ask quickly about Network Enabled Army?
Sure.
Because that's a period that it's been more than a decade now.
And I appreciate something's evolved.
Good example of Bushmaster-
Yeah
... tactical changes coming out of Ukraine.
Very good example. Are we making the necessary
progress to actually deliver something tangible that helps the
soldier in the field?
Yes, we are.
What I can say is, Network Enabled Army has
delivered a full suite of capability to our special forces.
It's delivered
all the strategic bearers, the SATCOM bearers-
Yeah
... that we need.
It's delivered over 1,200 radios now into Army.
We've got some more work to do, and there's more coming over the next two years.
We've got some more work to do to network those radios so that we can get
digital data down as low as we can so that individual
soldiers, if they need it, can get digital messaging
updates on a small iPad-type
system.
And we've proven the ability to move
digital information essentially from our joint headquarters to a
soldier in the field, through a series of layers of command.
What we now have to do is network horizontally across the system.
We're getting close to enough radios for the system,
and now the next piece of work is to get that horizontal integration working,
as well as some
things like the Bushmaster comms.
The other thing it has delivered is it's delivered
three uncrewed reconnaissance systems, remote
ground sensors, and we're just finishing off
an EW, an electronic warfare capability that we've just been
delayed going through the American system.
So it is really starting to pick up
some momentum. There is more work to do.
But when you say there's a piece of work to do to work on the horizontal, for
example-
Yeah
... is that us designing and building it, or is that us just going,
"There's a bunch of other military out in the world that do this already.
We'll have some of those, please"?
We are still doing a
level of design and build.
I think if we were to start this again, we would be likely to
follow more of the sort of approach you're outlining.
But NEA, from its outset, was quite
world-leading, and that's probably not a place we'd want to be in the future.
But the more that we do that, the more we commit to this, the more we just
involve in this bespoke system-
Supply
... which might not necessarily plug in with partners.
Are we not better to just go, "Actually, we need to start..."
Actually done,
we were out a little bit ahead of where Australia was at.
They took a slightly different route, and now we've realigned it to what
they're doing, for that very reason.
I think, like I say, if we were to start this now,
we would want to be a fast follower, not
put everything up front.
There isn't necessarily a company out there that just sells this, though.
That's the problem the world has. So every country around the world has had to put
together different companies to deliver it. It's not like a Lockheed.
There is no Lockheed Martin for Network Enabled Army.
And it would be very, very expensive.
We're often looking to see, is there a company that could come in and do
all of the integration and manage the whole thing?
But there's a combination of do we want to pay for that,
and what are they actually adding? What value are they actually adding?
But we're working with Australia, as Matt said.
We're using the Australian technical standards, so it's interoperable with
Australia.
Can I now move to the humanitarian peacekeeping side of that?
Sorry, I'll flip into that finishing that. You all right?
I'm fantastic.
Okay.
I think we may, thanks.
Oh, then can I just finish on that one while we're actually out there in the field-
... doing what soldiers do?
I understand the point about
it will cost more money.
Mm-hmm.
But the cost in terms of capacity to NZDF
to do this all-
Mm
... yourself
is pretty significant. And then, maybe this bespoke
system doesn't exist out there, but when we look back 30
years, we've had other people that have had some
level of this technology, whether it was Rover with Blue Force Trackers, all sorts
of things.
Are we genuinely that
world-leading that we're right at the front of this curve and no one else is doing
this?
I would say we've dropped back to a fast follower now.
Yeah.
So Australia has now- ... moved in front of us, which is good.
And now we can follow them. Part of the NEA program is we've also
built
a couple of facilities which will allow us to, as other
technologies come in, we can then start to integrate them into our system,
which will give us an ability to be a bit more agile going forward.
And it creates some capacity within the
NZDF to then
get a better sense of can a new system integrate with our current command and
control system or not. So, that's going to be an important facet of NEA
as we move forward into... Because all this technology's updating so fast,
it's a constant change.
Mm.
Can I just- Can I just, a question around our obligations
at Pacific and the, I guess, increasing frequency of
events,
climatic events and that. So the capability and capacity
that's been undermined temporarily with one of the boats going down, but,
the new frigate
purchase will have to incorporate a number of different objectives as a
platform.
How do we know that the focus on that humanitarian
support within the Pacific, which is a key part of our- Mm ...
our legal obligations, how do we know that you're going to incorporate that
capacity?
Should I start? I think in the maritime area,
yes, the frigate purchase will undoubtedly be focused on a combat capability.
We are already working with our Pacific partners,
in terms of providing the maritime domain awareness.
And there's a real concern around
transnational organized crime, and so we're doing some work
with our partners in that space, and we've utilized the Blue Bottles and some other
capabilities already to help.
Within the maritime fleet renewal program, there is also
patrol vessels. There's a whole bunch of uncrewed,
again, for maritime domain awareness.
And then we have the projection ship
project which will
update the sort of capability we have from HMMNZ Canterbury.
So that gives us the sea lift and logistics capacity,
to then provide support. Alongside that, of course, we've just
finished the C-130J project, which gives us really good
capacity into the Pacific and land projects.
One of the reasons we've gone for more light vehicles, in say the likes of
Australia had, is we're very focused on getting the right capabilities
into the Pacific, and a whole bunch of heavy armored vehicles don't meet
that need.
Mm.
So that's an area where we've actually diverged a bit from what the Australians are
doing because of our focus into the southwest Pacific rather
than kind of continental fighting.
Hmm.
One last thing, because a couple of minutes.
I flicked through this, and I haven't seen it
specified that the loss of the attrition rates
with personnel affecting the capability to actually
put these projects in place. You haven't highlighted that, but I
guess, is that a key part of the challenge going forward?
Yeah. So DCP, the Defense Capability Plan, is an
integrated plan, and it has lines of work around our
workforce. There is a strategic workforce
program
that is running now,
that it is around supply of people and the right people.
It's also about better workforce planning- ...
so we can project what we'll need to support or to
run the capabilities as they're prepared.
And if I looked at a big program like the maritime fleet renewal, the
people, the workforce is a central theme to that.
How do we get the right skills? How do we transform our training so that
our sailors have the right
military skills and competencies at the right time?
So it is a central piece, but it is a real challenge.
It's a national challenge to get
good
young talent.
STEM talent is in demand, and we're
in that competition.
Look, thank you very much for being on time.
And so appreciate the briefing. Thanks.
And we'll work out what to do from here. Thank you. That's great.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
Thanks for the questions guys. Nice to see you again.